Guide to Foreign Mission School Collection 1799-2015 MS 038 MS 038
Cornwall Historical Society
Foreign Mission School Collection
1799-2015
Cornwall Historical Society
MS 038
7 linear feet (15 boxes)
The Foreign Mission School Operated from 1817 to 1826 and educated 100 pupils from diverse backgrounds. The collection encompasses administrative, educational, and printed materials.
Provenance
This collection was compiled over many years by members of the Cornwall Historical Society
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
The Foreign Mission School was established in 1817 in Cornwall, Connecticut. Approximately 100 pupils were educated at the Foreign Mission School during its near 10 years of operation. The Foreign Mission School was a bold new venture in evangelism: to convert, and educate young men, predominantly people of color, from indigenous cultures around the world, and send them home to be native preachers, translators, teachers, and health workers. It was established by the American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions (ABCFM), who held the view that Christianity and civilization were inseparable gifts to be brought to non-christians.The students of the Foreign Mission School brought 24 different native languages to Cornwall and represented such places as Hawaii, China, and Greece.
The main subject taught at the Foreign Mission School was christian religion, though other subjects were covered as well. As part of their christian education students attended weekly services and their progress was reviewed annually at a public examination.
The founding pupil was Heneri Opukahaia, an unlettered 18-year-old Hawaiian refugee from a blood feud, left by a ship's captain in wintry New Haven in 1810. His circumstances inspired efforts to shelter and educate him and others, some from American Indian tribes, many displaced from great distances - Asia, Europe, Polynesia, and Africa - as missionaries. As an exponent of the ABCFM's vision, he traveled widely to preach its message, but he died in Cornwall at 26 before he could return home as a missionary. In 1993, the remains of Obookiah were exhumed and returned to Hawaii.
In time, questions were raised about this method of education and evangelization. Support for the Foreign Mission School had been slowly declining when the marriages of two Cornwall girls with Cherokee students caused a local furor and public scandal, this gave the ABCFM an opportunity to close the Foreign Mission School in 1826.
Scope and Content Note
The Foreign Mission School Collection encompasses material relating to and about the Foreign Mission School. The collection is organized into seven series, correspondence, legal materials, administrative materials, print materials, photohraphic and print images, realia, and miscellaneous.
The Correspondence series is comprised of letters inquiring about the Foreign Mission School and letters written by those who attended or were in some other way involved with the Foreign Mission School.
The Legal Materials in the collection are marriage certificates, land deeds, and census materials.
The materials in the Administrative series relate to the running of the Foreign Mission School.
The print materials includes many volumes of books used by students at the Forieng Mission School as well as newspapers and newsclippings from the time of the Foreign Mission School through the early 2000s.
The Photographs and Printed Images series contains mostly 20th century images of commemorations of the Foreign Mission School. There are also some 19th century lithographs.
The Realia series is comprised of gifts from commemoration celebrations, printing plates, and a lock of hair.
The Miscellaneous materials is made up of collections of research notes, recollections, and geneologies.
Arrangement
Folders are arranged alphabetically by subject/author heading then chronologically within each subject/author heading.
The files are grouped into 7 series:
Correspondence
Legal Materials
Administrative Materials
Print Materials
Photographs and Print Images
Realia
Miscellaneous
Foreign Mission School; Indians of North America--Education--History--19th Century; Hawaiians--Education--History--19th Century; Foreign Study--Connecticut; Student, Foreign--Connecticut; Church work with foreign students--Connecticut; Missions--Hawaii; Foreign Mission School, (Cornwall, Conn.)-students-biography; Cherokee Indians--History--Sources; Cherokee Indians--Biography; Military Chaplain--United States; Military Chaplains; Correspondence; Clippings; Newspapers; Pamphlets; Research Notes; Photographs; Xerographic copies; Books; Cornwall Historical Society; Obookiah,Henry--1792--1818; Patoo,Thomas Hamitah, approximately 1804-1823.; Boudinot, Elias, 1740-1821.; Fisk, Photius, -1890.
- Correspondence
  - Letters to Emily Marsh, 1937-1942 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Letters to Emily Marsh, 1943-1972 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Letters to E. C. Starr, 1890-1896 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Letters to E. C. Starr, 1890-1896 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Letters to E. C. Starr, 1897-1939 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Letters to E. C. Starr, 1897-1939 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - With CHS, 1966; , 1975-1981; , 2005-2007 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Deacon Lorrain Loomis to Photius Fisk, 1823; , 1840-1841 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - W. H. Miner to Rev. John Pierpont, 1895 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Gold Family, 1825-1845; , 1971 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Rev. Dwight Pratt, 1,817-1830; , 1874 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - John E. Calhoun, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Michael Gannett, 1934; , 1982-1993 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Timothy Stone, 1827 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Lyman Warner, 1891 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Henry Obookiah, 1815; , 1818 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - John Ridge, 1836; , 1854 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Ellen Gibbs, 1910 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - A-See, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - John Smith, 1826-1830 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Evarts, 1826-1827; , 1830 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Sarah Ridge, 1854 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Herman Daggett, 1895 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Legal Materials
  - Marriage certificates, 1824; , 1826 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    General
    Certificates for: John Ridge and Sally Northrup, Steven J Gold and Sarah F. Calhoun and Elias Boudinot and Harriet Gold.
  - Land Deeds for School, 1799; , 1817-1845; , 1873 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    Immediate Source of Acquisition
    Materials include: 1799 deed for town to build a school, American Board (which owned school) deed to Frederick Kellogg, Frederick Kellogg deed to the First Eclesiastical Society, notes on Seth Piece transaction, and copious photocopies of town record books.
  - Deed of Bacon/ Gracey House, undated (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Will of Photius Fisk, 1888 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Census of the Eastern Cherokee Nation, undated (Box 7, Folder 6-7)
    Materials are photocopies, and also include photocopies of some Mary C. Boudinot correspondence, her aid petition and the approval certificate.
  - Last Will and Testament of Elias Boudinot, undated (Box 7, Folder 5)
    This is the last will and testament of New Jersey merchant Elias Boudinot who sponsored the Cherokee student later called Elias Boudinot, and heavily supported missionary activities.
- Administrative Materials
  - Semi Annual Reports, 1825 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - List of Pupils, undated (Box 8, Folder 2-3)
  - Annual Meeting Programs and Related Materials, undated (Box 8, Folder 4)
    Program for annual meeting 1814 and 1820; George Weed chatechism book (written by Weed); book of poems and correspondence.
- Print Materials
  - Books
    - FMS Books (Box 6, Box 13, Box 14)
    - Chinese Memory Book, undated (Box 8, Folder 16)
      Two photocopied pages of and a letter related to a book called the Chinese Memory Book, in which the name of a former Foreign Mission School student appears.
    - Charles Aroherkeah's Commonplace book, 1822 (Box 8, Folder 14)
    - Autograph book by John Loy, undated (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Hawaiian Pronounciation Guide, 1967; , 1993 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Pamphlets
    - T. Dwight Sermon, 1813 (Box 2, Folder 11)
      Sermon was given in Boston to the ABCFM.
    - J. Harvey Sermon, 1815 (Box 2, Folder 12)
      Given to the Foreign Missionary Society of Litchfield County.
    - A Narrative of Five Youth from the Sandwich Islands, 1816 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - D. L. Perry Sermon, 1820 (Box 2, Folder 14)
      Given at the Annual Exams at the Foreign Mission School.
    - Religious Intelligencer, 1823 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Semicentennial of Foreign Mission School, 1861 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Commemorative address of the 50th anniversary of the first Hawaiian Missionary ordination, 1869 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Historical Sketch of Hawaiian Missions, 1871 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Historical Sketch of Missions of the American Board, 1872 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - History of the Foreign Mission Work in Litchfield County, 1876 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Ninth Annual Report of the Women's Board of Missions, 1880 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Historical Sketch of Missions with North American Indians, 1880 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Cherokee Indian History, 1884 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Magazine of American History, 1887 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - The Treasury of Religious Thought, 1893 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - One Hundred and Fiftieth Anniversary of the Congregational Church, 1893 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - The Hawaiian Islands, 1896 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Cut Gems for Sermon Settings, 1896 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Condensed Historical Sketch of the American Board, 1897 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - The Church at Home and Abroad, 1898 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Thirteenth Annual Record of the Congregatiol Church, 1899 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - The Hawaiian Islands, 1899 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Manual of the First Church of Christ, 1900 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Hawaii Hawaii, 1902 (Box 3, Folder 11)
      Promotional booklet about Hawaii after it became a United States Territory.
    - The Missionary Herald, 1904 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - The American Missionary, 1905 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Papers of Hawaiian Historical Society, 1908 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Gist the Central Baptist Church, 1909 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - The American Missionary, 1909 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - The Missionary Herald, 1910 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - The Fifth Number of the Pastors Series, 1910 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Elias Boudinot on account of his life, 1913 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - The Life and Light for Women, 1916 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Centennial Celebration of the Congregational Church, 1919 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Hawaiian Mission Centennial, 1920 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Early Hawaiian Churches, 1924 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Master's Thesis Oscar P. Bollman, 1939 (Box 4, Folder 5-6)
    - The Missionary Herald, 1940-1941 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Morning Star and Missionary Packet, 1942; 1947 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - The Old Mission Houses, 1945 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Hawaiian Mission Children's Society, 1952 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Extract from yearbook of the American Philosophical Society, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - The Cherokee and the Deacon's Daughter, 1963 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - The story of Imolia Congregational Church, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - One Hundred and Fiftieth Anniversary of the death of Henry Obookiah, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Inserts to Cornwall Village, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Influence of One Man, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Promotion Ad for Missionary Album, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Kawaiahao Church, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Sunday Star Bulletin and Advertiser, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Good News by a Guy named Luke, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Journal of the New Haven Colony Historical Society, 1978 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Hawaii Journal of History, 1981 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - The United Church of Christ, 1993 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Owhihe Language, 1993 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Native American Magazine, 2000 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - High School Paper by Suzanne Iwanicki, 2002 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - The New England Quarterly, 2003 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Presentation on the Chinese Friendship Album, 2005 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Memoir of Thomas H. Patoo, undated (Box 5, Folder 10)
      Student of the Foreign Mission School from the Marquesas, who died while a student at the Foreign Mission School.
    - How the Gospel came to Hawaii, undated (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Henry Obookiah related print materials, undated (Box 5, Folder 12)
      One pamphlet titled "Obookiah, a native of Owyhee", and one handbook from the Henry Obookiah School in Hilo, Hawaii.
    - The Story of Mokuaikaua Church, undated (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Promotional Materials, undated (Box 5, Folder 14)
      Materials include: pamphlet for the Mariner's Church in San Francisco, California, pamphlet for historic missionary housing in Honolulu, and one brochure for a walking tour of monarchy promonade in Honolulu, Hawaii.
    - The Butterick Transfer 10393, 10494, undated (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - Miscellaneous Print Materials, undated (Box 5, Folder 16)
      Materials include: postcard of Hawaii, part of a children's book on Hawaiian history, an article on Union Congregational Church in Wailuku, Hawaii, memo regarding Hawaiian visitors to CHS and two excerpts from missionary journals.
    - The National Historic Landmark Nomination, 2015 (Box 5, Folder 17)
    - Geophysical Field Assistance Survey, 2015 (Box 5, Folder 18)
      Conducted by Nicholas Bellantoni.
    - The First Foreign School in America, undated (Box 5, Folder 19)
    - New England Looks Outward, 1969 (Box 5, Folder 20)
    - Torringford, 1944 (Box 5, Folder 21)
      Copy of a publication called Torringford, copied section relates to Henry Obookiah.
    - Connecticut History, 2007 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Newspapers and Clippings
    - The Itacha Democrat, 1898 (Box OS 1, Folder 1)
    - The Christian Mirror, 1828; , 1830 (Box OS 1, Folder 2)
    - Daily Witness Relating to Photius Fisk, 1842 (Box OS 1, Folder 3)
    - Cherokee Advocate, 1897 (Box OS 1, Folder 4)
    - Cherokee Phoenix, 1831 (Box OS 1, Folder 5)
    - Litchfield County, 1824; , 1864-1894; , 1902 (Box OS 1, Folder 6)
    - New Haven County, 1930; , 1959-1968 (Box OS 1, Folder 7)
    - Massachusetts and New York, 1910; , 1941 (Box OS 1, Folder 8)
    - Hawaii, 1968-1970 (Box OS 1, Folder 9)
    - Miscellaneous, 1899; , 1900-1965 (Box OS 1, Folder 10)
    - Boston Weekly Messenger, 1818 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Four Print Out Hawaiian Youths, 1822 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Religious Intellingencer, 1831 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Public Letter from Andrew Jackson, 1835 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - The Winsted Herald, 18801893 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Dwight Mission Witness, 1886 (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - The Hartford Daily Times, 1894 (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - The Outlook, 1896 (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - Oneida, 1898-1899 (Box 10, Folder 9)
    - Sketch of Reverend Edwin Dwight, 1907 (Box 10, Folder 11)
    - The Friend, 1903; , 1925 (Box 10, Folder 10)
    - Newsclippings, 1900; , 1909-1916 (Box 10, Folder 12)
    - Chronicles of Oklahoma, 1929 (Box 10, Folder 13)
    - Cherokee Soil, 1952 (Box 10, Folder 14)
    - The Christian Science Monitor, 1954; , 1959 (Box 10, Folder 15)
    - Early Georgia, 1955; , 1957 (Box 10, Folder 16)
    - The Friend, 1968 (Box 10, Folder 18)
    - Henry Obookiah Memorial Service, 1960; , 1968 (Box 10, Folder 17)
    - Sesquicentennial Spectator, 1970 (Box 10, Folder 19)
    - The Lakeville Journal and The Waterbury Republican, 1972 (Box 10, Folder 20)
    - Artifacts, 1981-1982 (Box 10, Folder 21)
    - The Waterbury Republican, 1989 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Exhumation of Henry Obookiah, 1993 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - Memoirs of Henry Obookiah a Rhetorical History, 2005 (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - Northwest Corner Journal, 2010 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - The Maui News, 2011 (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - Newsclippings, undated (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - James Ely related clippings, 1894; , undated (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - Photius Fisk related clippings, 1882; , undated (Box 11, Folder 8)
    - FMS related newsclippings, 1940-1941 (Box 11, Folder 9)
    - Honolulu Star Bulletin, The Friend, and Paradise of the Pacific copies, 1859; , 1920-1940; , 1954-2003 (Box 11, Folder 10)
    - Boudinot related clippings, 1890; , 1905 (Box OS 1, Folder 11)
- Photographs and Printed Images
  - James King Photo and a sign, undated (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Henry Obookiah Exumation, 1993 (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Hawaiian Monument Kealakekua Bay, 1925; , 1968 (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Obookiah grave Kona, 1994 (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - Prints of Obookiah, undated (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - Chinese Visitors, 2005 (Box 9, Folder 17)
  - Henry Obookiah grave Cornwall Connecticut, undated (Box 9, Folder 18)
  - Harriett Gold House, undated (Box 9, Folder 19)
  - Photius Fisk, undated (Box 9, Folder 20)
  - London, undated (Box 9, Folder 21)
  - Foreign Mission School, 1873 (Box 9, Folder 22)
  - Dedication of Grave Marker, 1970 (Box 9, Folder 23)
  - Memorial Ceremony, 1940 (Box 9, Folder 24)
- Realia
  - Boudinot Daughter's Hair, undated (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Kapa Cloth, undated (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Printing Plates, undated (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Henry Obookiah Grave Marker, 1970 (Object Item 1)
  - Obookiah Memorial gifts, 1940; , 1982 (Box OS 2)
  - Obookiah Memorial gift Leis, 1940 (Box OS 3)
  - Tapa Cloth Paper, undated (Box 9, Folder 1)
- Miscellaneous
  - James Ely Religious Papers, 1828 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Photius Fisk Papers, undated (Box 7, Folder 10)
    Materials include: Longfellow Memorial Association certificate, poems, and a commission from the President of the Greek Republic.
  - Bibliography of Edwin Dwight, undated (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Heman Daggett Papers, undated (Box 7, Folder 12)
    Materials include: book of correspondence to Hawaiian students that had returned home, Daggett family genealogic information, and Daggett's master's thesis.
  - Reverend E. C. Starr Papers, undated (Box 7, Folder 11)
    Materials include: biographical information on John Ridge's father, notes on Elias Boudinot, receit, Religious journal receipts for Religious Intelligencer, Order form for the Pilgrim Series, notes on the founding of the Foreign Mission School, manuscript on the life of Henry Obookiah and copies of a typescript of a piece titled "The Foreign Mission School.
  - Cornelius Everest Papers, undated (Box 7, Folder 9)
    Materials include: notes by E.C. Starr on Everest family, and two copies of a sermon delivered by Everest in Windham Connecticut.
  - Manuscript of Mrs. Cowles, 1890; , 1892 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    Cowles notes about her personal recollections of Henry Obookiah and the Foreign Mission School.
  - T. S. Gold Speech, 4 October 1967 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    T.S. Gold, the younger's, speech about Cornwall industry given at the Falls Village Historical Society.
  - Excerpt from The History of Goshen, undated (Box 8, Folder 7)
    Excerpt is regarding ministers related to the foreign mission movement, specifically that Joseph Harvey of Goshen was instumental in getting the Foreign Mission School established in Litchfield County.
  - Cupid helped to close Cornwall mission school, undated (Box 8, Folder 8)
    Typescript about the controversial marriages that occured between students of the Foreign Mission School and local women.
  - Editor's preface by Edwin Wolfe, undated (Box 8, Folder 9)
    Appeared in the WBM 150th Anniversary Edition; preface is about Henry Obookiah.
  - Reminiscences by Benjamin Welch Pettibone, undated (Box 8, Folder 10)
    Pettibone's notes on the history of the Foreign Mission School being started and information on Deacon Lorrain Loomis, steward of the Foreign Mission School.
  - A. Hodson's "Journey through America", undated (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Hirman Bingham 50th Anniversay, undated (Box 8, Folder 12)
    A hymn sung at the 50th anniversary of Bingham's ordination as a missionary in Goshen, CT.
  - Transcript of Poem about Henry Obookiah, 1820 (Box 8, Folder 13)
    Poem about the death of Henry Obookiah published in the Hartford Mirror.
  - Translation of Chinese Friendship Book, undated (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - Henry Obookiah Memorial Services, 1919; , 1940-1960; , 1993 (Box 8, Folder 17)
    Materials include: programs, receipts, a play and speeches.
  - Drawing of FMS by Carlotte Clark, undated (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - Lead Pipe Label, undated (Box 8, Folder 19)
  - Application for Membership of the 1st Eccl. Society, 1827 (Box 8, Folder 20)
    Application of Stephen J. Gold and three transcribed copies of original application.
  - Notes by B. W. Welch, undated (Box 9, Folder 2)
    Notes from Hughes History of St. Lawrence and Franklin Counties, New York.
  - Invitation to Obookiah Memorial Ceremony in Hawaii, undated (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Description of Journey of Adam Hodgson, undated (Box 9, Folder 5)
    Notes, in modern script, of the travels of Adam Hodgson, a British man from Liverpool, through New England and the southern Cherokee settlements.
  - Folsom Genealogy, undated (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Foreign Mission School citations, undated (Box 9, Folder 8)
    Lists of citations for Foreign Mission School in different collections and print works.
  - Ann Schillinger notes on FMS, undated (Box 9, Folder 9)
    Foreign Mission School experts research notes relating to various aspects of the foreign mission school.